recording in progress.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. I
would like to call the August 10th
meeting of the governing body to order
and ask the clerk if she would take the
role, please.
>> Mr. Esel,
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> here.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> Dr. Renie,
>> present.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> present.
>> Mr. Wolf, Dr. Aldrich,
>> present. Mayor Collins
>> here.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Two members are absent. We do have a
quorum.
>> Would you please join me in the pledge
of allegiance? Mr. ESel is here for the
record.
>> Aliance to the flag of the United States
of America and to the republic for it
stands. One nation,
indivisible, with liberty and justice
for all.
Consent
agenda. All agenda items listed with the
designation of CA are considered to be
routine items by the governing body and
will be enacted by one motion. There
will be no separate discussion on these
items unless a member of the governing
body. So requests and support by two
other members is received. Any item
removed from the consent agenda will be
considered in its normal sequence on the
agenda.
>> All right. Is there any items some
member of the governing body would like
to remove from the consent agenda?
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir. Mr. Mayor,
>> uh 10 A. Concur.
>> That is the legacy construction for
Christensen Road Detention. Is there a
second concurrence?
>> Second.
>> Okay, we'll take 10A off. Anybody else?
>> Hearing none, I would entertain a
motion.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> yes.
>> I have a conflict with H Bravo. I am
going to recuse myself.
>> Okay.
>> It's been moved by Mr. Caggrave. Is
there a second?
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. All those in
favor of the consent agenda with 10A
removed, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. 10 A or the consented as
approved. 10A has been removed and uh
Dr. Rainey has declared a conflict.
Number six, ordinance third reading,
amending or I'm sorry, annexing to the
city of Cheyenne, Wyoming land west of
Roundtop Road and south of HappyJack
Road.
>> All right, we have an owner initiated
annexation. Um, this is on third
reading. Is there anybody in the
audience would like to speak to this
annexation?
>> Miss Madrid,
Heather Madrid. I live in Ward One. Um,
I am opposed to this annexation and
every other annexation until necessary
changes are made to the UDC, among other
things. Um, the city has spent the last
several years annexing and reszoning
small properties like this with the
intent of slowly but surely connecting
to a massive parcel which will inevit
inevitably become a business park. This
happened with a Swan Ranch. It's you're
attempting to do this with the Cox Ranch
and have attempted to do this with the
Bison Business Park, just to name. I'm
sure there's more, but that's all that I
can think of off the top of my head. Um,
conversely, you have been annexing
properties whose owners don't want to be
annexed because you claim you need to
resolve county pockets. Meanwhile, with
your arbitrary annexations, you've
created a massive county pocket in South
Cheyenne. Um, the the map, the city map
actually look kind of looks like a joke.
It it it is anything but logical and
feasible. Um you hide behind a
clandestine relationship with Cheyenne
leads and their board members which is
fortified by a non-disclosure agreement.
Not surprisingly, the board of leads
finds property owners who are unknowing
of their true intent. These property
owners are often asked to sign non
non-disclosure agreements themselves,
which is one of the many ways Meta snuck
into a residential
leads and its members are acting in bad
faith and omitting the information that
the end goal is heavy industrialization,
which blindsides the property owner and
the neighbors. These property owners are
then represented by AVI Engineering
during their so-called owner initiated
annexation project. AVI engineering is a
board member of Cheyenne Leads and thank
you for recusing yourself for that. I I
can't I genuinely appreciate that very
much. Um
AVI engineering is the applicant for
this particular annexation.
Um I believe the NDA with Cheyenne leads
needs to be terminated. I don't think
that it it was signed in bad faith or
you know I understand that the thought
was that it needed to be done but the
result has been that we can't trust you
anymore.
Um,
I think that the contract with Cheyenne
Leads needs to be dissolved because they
are currently getting public money to
make economic recommendations
um,
without telling us. for example, the
Traml Crow proposal, which is the newest
data center proposal that we're going to
be seeing pretty soon, which everybody
seemed to be in the dark about except
for, you know, I'm sure you I'm sure you
probably knew and Cheyenne Leeds knew.
Um, but I don't but the county didn't
know, the council didn't know. I find I
that's a problem. It really is.
Um,
leadeds is making recommendations to
develop projects and properties that
benefit them and their members
financially.
And until there is an ethics ordinance
in place, I cannot support any
annexations, no matter the size or the
verbal commitments, because I cannot
trust that we're getting the whole story
with any with any of it. Thank you.
Good evening.
>> All right. Good evening.
>> Pull that microphone up so we can hear
you better, please.
>> Okay. Is that a lot better?
>> Much better. Thank you so much.
>> Yeah. I'm uh Brian Pixley. I've been a
resident at the Roundtop in uh and have
Jack for a very long time and uh I'm I'm
totally opposed against this data
center, you know, so and like that, but
you tend to listen to all these people
from California and all that stuff and
you know, and everything else, but you
don't listen to us voters and
everything. And I I feel like I'm
silenced and you know, a peasant, you
know, so I just I just told you that I'm
I'm opposed to it. So I don't want it.
So and
that's all I got to say. So I thought
I'd speak to my mind and tell them no on
all annexations, you know, because we
don't know what the future's going to uh
tell, you know, and it kind of sounds
like, you know, like land killers if you
ask me. So okay, thank you.
>> Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to the uh annexation before us on
third reading?
Jennifer
>> uh Bardmus Smith, you can unmute
yourself.
>> Mr. Miller.
Mr. Miller.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
All right. Could you just confirm
the
agenda item that we're on currently?
>> Mr. Miller, do you have anything to say?
>> Hello. I'm sorry.
>> Do you have anything to say? We're we're
asking for your testimony.
>> Um
Charles Miller for the record. uh
>> the
uh the previous speaker speakers have uh
pretty much uh exemplified
what I was going to say. I just I just
want to agree
uh with them and uh I will pass it
along. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none, we'll go to Dr.
Aldrich for a motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so move
second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens. Comments from
members of the governing body on the
annexation.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I just would like
to clarify
um from my own education, the purpose of
this is for a parking lot. Is that not
correct? I believe it's for a storage a
layown facility to support um the
construction of a data center. They need
a place to be able to store or to to uh
pile up the equipment they'll need while
they're doing the the construction.
>> But it's excuse me uh through your it's
not an actual data center. Is that
correct?
>> Uh no ma'am.
>> Thank you.
>> Dr. Rainey, did you have a comment sir?
Anybody else? Hearing none. Madame
clerk, would you take the vote?
>> Dr. Mr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Escobel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> No.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Yes.
>> This annexation is approved on third and
final reading with Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Number seven. Ordinance third reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of BP business
park for land annex to the city of
Cheyenne located west of Roundtop Road
and south of HappyJack Road.
>> All right. State law says we got to give
it a city zone and uh our uh planning
department tries to establish the zone
that's closest to the county zone and
the the uses that are in the area and uh
that would be BP. We'll go out to the
audience if anybody wants to speak to
the zone district before us.
Miss Madrid,
>> Heather Madre, Ward One. Um, I recognize
that this the business park loophole is
a state level issue. However, in 2022,
a definition for data centers was
created which allowed them to be used by
right. That happened here, not at the
state. um rather than having them be
continue to be conditional use. This
shifted the approvals from a case-byase
public review to an administrative
decision. This is how we will end up
with five separate Microsoft data
centers in the existing Bison Business
Park, but don't know anything about it
until it's announced in the mayor's
minute. Um just a side note, leadeds
considers these five data centers as one
um in the official numbers that they
share with the public.
Um seems like Cheyenne Leeds has the
reigns of the city along with the
planning department. And I'm curious if
the planning department signs
non-disclosures or if Board of Public
Utilities, Black Hills Energy, etc.
signs non-disclosures with leads or any
of these developers or operators.
>> I think we can answer that question.
That is no.
>> Thank you.
um telling us that our fight is with the
state is lazy and is another halftruth.
This council and planning department
have made many changes to local zoning
regulations that allow data centers to
be fast-tracked in business parks while
the citizens are sidelined.
So similar to annexations, I cannot
support any resonings especially for
light industrial, heavy industrial,
multi- whatever the other
data center one is and business parks
until the locally created loophole that
piggybacks off the existing state
loophole um is closed and until the NDAs
are terminated and the contract with
leads is dissolved and there's ethics
ordinances in place. Unfortunately,
for all the reasons I just mentioned, we
cannot trust you anymore. And we did not
elect, with all due respect to the
people that I'm about to name, I
understand they're doing their job, but
we did not elect Betsy Hail or Brad
Evans or Connor White or Charles Bloom,
but it seems like they are in charge
while most of this council is in the
dark about upcoming projects and current
projects. And I again, I find that to be
very problematic. Thank you,
>> Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Charles Miller, for the record, um, if
this 34 acre parcel is truly just for a
construction staging yard and office
trailers, why is this council voting to
assign it a permanent business park BP
zoning classification tonight? Why not
assign it a lighter temporary holding
classification?
>> Anything else you want to say, Mr.
Miller?
>> Uh, yeah. Under the Cheyenne, uh, under
Cheyen's Unified Development Code, once
a property is zone BP, data centers are,
as Miss Madrid said, permitted by right.
This means that once the council votes
yes on item seven tonight, the developer
never has to come back to this council
or the public for a vote to build a
high- noise, high utility data center on
those 34 acres. They can bypass public
hearings entirely through a purely
administrative site plan.
Um, on May 4th, 2026, during the
Cheyenne Planning Commission meeting,
city planner Connor White explicitly
admitted that that developers use the BP
zone to bypass public notice and council
votes. Quote unquote, if you take
several of the parcels and they wanted
to combine them into one, that'd be an
administrative plat and then an
administrative site plan. The zone
districts in this area already allow for
data centers as a use by right. And on
July 20th, 2026, Brad Emmens, the
developers agent from AVI, admitted to
the public services committee that the
annexation's true purpose is to expand
the industrial footprint, not just house
trailers. Part of the reason to get
annexed is so they can combine lots and
expand the North Range Business Park.
So, moving forward to make sure we can
combine and expand, quote unquote. Um,
yeah. If if this is just a staging yard,
will the council amend tonight's
ordinance to explicitly prohibit data
centers on this parcel?
Um and and if you refuse, then you're
actively hiding a by industrial
um expansion behind a construction
trailer permit. Um the the staff report
claims this annexation is urgent to
protect the health, safety, and welfare
of the area by connecting it to city
water. But didn't this governing body
already approve an outside user
agreement for city water on this exact
parcel on June 22nd, 2026? Why the
sudden rush to annex and reszone this
land tonight if you guys already have
legal access to municipal water? Um
it's this is a rapid maneuver to capture
city jurisdiction so you can instant
instantly apply this BP zoning before
the public can organize.
Um, the Board of Public Utilities has
previously confessed on the record that
our agricultural aquifer has already
been siphoned down by 80 ft due to
industrial growth. Local residents in
Rolling Hills and the surrounding county
are already testifying that they are
experiencing immediate terrifying drops
in their private times up. Thank you.
Anybody else in the audience?
Hearing none, we'll go talk to Dr.
Aldridge. Thank you, ma'am.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Seagrave. Comments for
members of the governing body on the
establishment of the business park zone
district.
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk,
>> Mayor Collins,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Esel,
>> I.
>> Mr. Lebornne,
>> hi.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> no.
>> Dr. Ry,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Mr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Uh, the established zone district is
approved on third and final reading with
Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Next item is number 10 A on page two.
Consideration of bid number S-22-26
for a contract between the city of
Cheyenne and Legacy Construction Group
for the Christensen Road detention
erosion mitigation project.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Maybe start with Mr. Cobb. Are we we
ready to move this forward or what's
your brothers? Mayor, um to to you and
the city council. Um today I did meet
with UP representatives. I looks like
I'm going to have to put a second
alternative together. Um I would ask for
your discretion on this one. I'm now
adding a a bit of steel pipe to be able
to account for a future track. Um and
I'm also adding some erosion protection
within the ditch and placing an inlet at
the rideway. So this alternative is a
bit differently than what they've seen
before. So I need to give them just a
bit more time. I'd ask with your a
little bit of a latitude and for the
last time another two-e postponement and
then after that I will officially end it
after they see the second proposal. Sir
>> and two weeks will be enough sir.
>> Mayor uh [laughter]
directly to I I sincerely doubt it but
I'm I'm optimistic sir. I'm going to try
to keep this contract in place and for
at least to allow me to discuss options
with our contractors so that they can
properly schedule the rest of their
fall.
>> All right. Anybody else in the audience
want to speak to this contract? Um,
Christensen Road detention erosion
project.
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Uh Charles Miller, for the record,
um August 4th,
uh
oh, I'm sorry. Uh Mr. Mayor, members of
the council. Um, item number 10A,
uh, bid number S226,
you're asking, uh, taxpayers to approve
a $314,95
contract for a project that discharges
directly onto the active rightaway of
the United Union Pacific Railroad. Yet
during the August 4th, 2026 finance
committee meeting, city engineer Tom
Cobb openly admitted on a live
microphone that the city did not have a
signed written agreement from the
railroad to execute this project. Has
this changed? I'm sorry, I didn't I
didn't catch that. He had
uh gotten that contract signed.
>> I think Mr. Cobb just answered that
question. What else do you have to say?
>> I
um so he's he's Was that a no? I'm
sorry,
>> Mr. Cobb answered that question
just before you came online.
>> I apologize. My internet is a little
shoddy here.
>> He said,
>> "Would you
>> He said he's asked for a twoe
postponement so he can finish uh
finalize a an agreement with the
railroad."
>> Oh, okay. Okay. Um well, the
uh Okay. Okay. So, I guess there's uh
just one other thing I was wondering
about this. Uh
the
where is it here? Um it so in the agenda
it says $314,95
yet on July 27th the finance committee
officially recommended the bid in a
different amount uh in 314,950.
I would uh why is there a $45
mathematical mismatch on the face of
tonight's agenda?
>> I'm not aware there's a difference, sir.
I think this number has been consistent,
and I'm not sure that $45 makes that
much difference.
>> Well, uh this complete failure of basic
basic due diligence before signing major
real estate and construction deals is a
systemic habit for this administration
as you, Mr. mayor uh have laughed
[clears throat] um about during the July
29th goal setting review. The city
bought a commercial office building on
16th Street without checking the
plumbing only to realize after the sale
closed that the toilet was hooked to a
garden hose. Um you can't run a city by
buying buildings with garden hose
toilets and you cannot award $314,000
erosion contracts on active railroad
lines without a physically signed
easement in your hands. Thank you.
Anybody
else in the audience want to speak on
this contract
or this bid?
Hearing none, we'll go to Mr. Mr. White.
Excuse me.
>> I p I pitched head for Mr. Escoal.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to accept the bid
in an amount not to exceed $314,95.
And I so moved.
>> Second. Been seconded by Mr. Moody.
Mr. Mr. White, would you make the motion
to postpone, please?
>> Certainly. Mr. Mayor, I move for a twoe
postponement to this item.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody. We'll go out to
the audience on a twoe postponement.
Anybody want to talk about that?
>> How about from the governing body?
>> Yes, sir.
>> It's Dr. Aldridge. Mayor Collins, um I
am wondering about that if the um
engineering or the methodology is going
to change on this um with the
requirement of additional an additional
outlet and more pipe and additional
track I think is what uh engineer cop
said. um which I'm wondering if that
will change the bid amount once Legacy
has a chance to um look at the new
engineering proposal once it comes back
from the railroad if it wouldn't be uh a
better option to vote this down and what
would be the I guess the question is
what would be the benefit from
postponing rather than because it's
going to be changing an amount as well I
would assume then just voting this down
and starting fresh once we have that
agreement from the railroad.
>> Mr. Cob,
>> through you to Dr. Aldridge. So, Dr.
Aldridge, the reason that I've postponed
this long, I already had them put a
proposal together on what the railroad
really wanted, which was steel pipe
throughout the entire rideway. That
would have taken the contract amount up
another $280,000.
And then I would have recommended to you
that we actually reject the bids and
rebid this at a later date. So, what I'm
trying to do when I bring this forward
to you next is I will have a change
order amount for you that will be part
of that contract amendment in the in the
two weeks after I've got this railroad
approval.
>> Does that make sense, ma'am?
>> Yes, sir. A follow-up question.
>> Yes, ma'am.
I I just what what would we lose by
voting this down and just coming back
with a clean um resolution or a clean
item for a future agenda?
>> Mayor, through you to Dr. Aldridge.
Ma'am, I'll have to rebid the project if
it comes in the way they want it to do
because it it significantly changed the
bid. The benefit to the taxpayer and to
all of you is right now I've got a
contractor on hand that can fix a
problem that's been there for about five
years. We already have permitted by the
railroad for the use that we have. We
have a rightway we have a rightaway
utility permit within their rideway
right now. The erosion problem occurred
unbeknownst to us. We didn't we didn't
have any idea what was going on. They
didn't know what was going on. It was
discovered when a utility line was
exposed by Black Hills Energy and that's
what started the whole thing. But the
benefit is it's going to take me right
now if I can move this forward. It's
it's going to expedite the time and save
the taxpayer quite a bit of money. If we
have to rebid the thing, it's it's going
to be a lot longer process and it will
be more expensive.
>> Thank you.
>> Any questions from the governing body on
the postponement?
All right, hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The postponement is
approved.
Next item is number 11 A on page three,
voucher report.
>> Is there anybody in the audience or in
the governing body that would like to
speak to the vouchers?
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
Uh Charles Miller for the permanent
record here. Uh
mayor, members of the council, my
comments are strictly gerine to item
11A, tonight's voucher report totaling
1,810,9127
for the period of July 20th through
August 3rd.
A municipal budget is a zero sum ledger.
Every dollar approved tonight for luxury
entertainment, graphic design, and
aesthetic projects is a dollar actively
diverted from core failing public health
infrastructure. On December 22nd, 2025,
Mayor Patrick Collins admitted on the
record that replacing Cheyenne's toxic
lead water service lines is a massive,
completely unfunded crisis. quote, "It's
going to be our responsibility in the
future to replace those lead services
and correct that problem, and that is a
hundred million or more dollar um ask
for our community. It could even be
twice that much money." We are told
there is no money in the general fund to
replace these pipes, forcing families to
use plastic water filtering pictures.
Yet, tonight's voucher report reveals
that when it comes to non-essential
entertainment and aesthetics, the city's
pocketbook is limitless. I direct your
attention to the following exact
dispersements in tonight's ledger.
$41,800
in total talent fees for a single
weekend entertainment series, including
$30,500 paid to Lit Live, Inc. on August
3rd and $10,150
paid to Agency for Performing Arts LLC.
Uh two uh $1,887
paid toilets on the go for the mayor's
parade and $400 paid to Jared Hineselman
for a single bike to work graphic
design.
$4,793.65
65 paid to Kmart Company for train depot
ornaments and Capitol Dome ornaments.
$3,621
paid to SNJ Signs for traffic control to
move inactive Southern Pacific tourist
rail cars on 15th Street. Furthermore,
we see immense procedural waste in
tonight's bill list. The city is paying
$1,49.20
20 per month for a single copier in
community recreation and events.
Combining a $97920
lease to Pak Solutions with a $70
maintenance contract to exceed document
solutions while simultaneously paying
separate unconolidated
copier bills across IT, compliance, and
council. You cannot legally or ethically
claim financial insolveny regarding a
public health emergency while
simultaneously laundering hundreds of
thousands of uh discretionary dollars
through the consent agenda for fancy
fences, cosmetic curb repairs, and
>> thank you. Anybody else,
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes.
>> Just in response to that, the the slip
just approved $20 million to the city um
for lead pipe abatement. So,
>> something to celebrate, right?
We at least are getting a start on it.
>> Yes, sir. Anybody else either on the
governing body or in the audience that'd
like to speak to the vouchers?
>> I hear none. Next item, please.
>> 11B. the announcement of a public
hearing to be held August 24th, 2026 at
6:00 p.m. in city council chambers,
21101 O'Neal Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming,
and via electric conference electronic
conference meeting for a transfer of
location and ownership of retail liquor
license application filed with the city
clerk's office for Capital City
Hospitality LLC doing business as
Wyoming discount liquor 3501 East
Lincolnway, Cheyenne, Wyoming. License
currently held by 1734 Partners LLC,
1734 Metalland Drive, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
Other business.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience that would like to speak to the
governing body under other business?
>> All right. Hearing none, how about from
the governing body?
>> Sir,
>> Dr. Aldridge. Uh, Mayor Collins, I just
wanted to remind everyone that we will
have the council and coffee for Ward 3
uh this upcoming Saturday at Dosbog
located at East Persian and College in
the Persian marketplace from 9 to 11:00.
It's a drop in dropout event and so we
would welcome uh anyone who would like
to visit with us. Um, you don't have to
live in W 3 to attend. Um, we also want
I wanted to remind everyone that
Tuesday, August 18th, will be our
primary election here in Cheyenne where
we will where we will be uh selecting um
individuals that will go on to the
general election for the council as well
as our six penny ballot projects. So, I
would encourage everyone to vote uh
regardless of how you vote, please vote.
>> Mr. White, did you have a comment, sir?
>> I did not.
>> Okay,
>> I do.
>> Dr. Em.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor, um I wanted to
remind everyone that Sunday at 1:00 is
the um miniature golf tournament as a
fundraiser for the Botanic Garden. And I
have been negligent inounding you all to
get teams together, but I'm sure that
you can still do that. So, if anyone's
interested, um that's the annual
fundraiser and you can call the Botanic
Garden for that. Thank you,
>> Mr. White. I did have a comment. Thank
you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I forgot to announce
or to remind folks that this weekend is
also depot days, so folks can go to the
depot. Um, there'll be tours of the Big
Boy. You'll have to sign a waiver. We'll
use the trolley to fu uh folks over to
uh the roundhouse and um so tours of the
Big Boy, the 4014 will be going on most
of the weekend.
Aviation festival too, right?
>> There is the aviation.
>> Yeah, aviation festival.
>> Lots of fun things going on.
>> All right. Anybody else? If not, I would
entertain a motion to go in executive
session.
>> So move.
>> Actually, I think Mr.
>> C's got it. The official language.
>> Mr. Mayor, pursuant to Wyoming statute
section 164405A3,
I move that the governing body meet in
executive session to consider or receive
any information classified as
confidential by law.
>> Second.
>> All right. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> So guys, normally I tell you that when
we're done, we're just going to uh
adjourn. Uh I'm not sure that that's
going to be the case this time. We're
going to talk about some legal issues
and the governing body might have
direction when we get done. So, we're
going to move into to executive session
and then when we're done, we'll come
back and uh we'll either vote on that
motion or we'll vote to uh postpone. Uh
so, we're going to move into a different
room. You can stay here if you'd like
and um we'll come back uh when we're
finished. Thank you.
[clears throat]
Sir, it looks like we're going to be
debating for just a little bit longer
and then I'll meet with you right after.
Okay,
[snorts]
>> hang on a second.
>> All right, I'd like to call the uh
meeting of the governing body. [snorts]
That was easy for me to say. The
governing body back to order.
Um our executive session is done and
I'll turn it over to Mr. Crave uh for a
motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, [clears throat]
I move to authorize the city attorney to
investigate, prepare, and in the
exercise of the city attorney's
professional judgment to commence and
prosecute a declaratory judgment action
under the uniform declaratory judgments
act seeking a judicial determination of
whether an annexation ordinance is
subject to the municipal referendum
process or whether the annexation
challenge procedure
of Wyoming statute 15149
controls to the exclusion of the
referendum.
>> Second. It's been moved by Mr. Crave,
seconded by Mr. Esabel that we direct
the city attorney. And uh we'll go out
to the audience and see if anybody in
the audience wants to talk about the um
motion before us.
>> I see none. We'll go back to the
governing body. Dr. Aldridge. Mayor
Collins. Um I would just like to um
make known the reason I am going to vote
for this tonight. And the reason for
that is because I really believe that if
um it would be helpful to have um a
declaration from a um court of law
letting us know whether um the
annexation ordinance um
referendum can be done um and how and
what our limitations would be in that
response. I think that um while um our
city clerk will continue to count the
signatures and that process is moving
forward, um it will be helpful to have
some sort of a decision made by the
courts as to if that's actually what is
meant by our state statutes as far as a
referendum being available uh as a
remedy for um a concern that's been
brought forward by citizens um in order
to save time and energy moving forward.
forward on behalf of the citizens who
have signed these petitions and on
behalf of our uh city staff. For that
reason, I'll be a yes vote tonight.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Mayor, um just for the same reasons
as as my colleague from W three made.
The only reason I'd be supporting this
and I do want this because I want some
guidance for both future governing
bodies and citizens. Um but the only
reason that I'm that tipped the scales
for me to support this is that the ref
the petition that was submitted and
received still continues forward. There
will be a decision certification will be
made one way or the other uh on that
petition that was received. So it in no
way precludes that from continuing
through the process. Just wanted to
point that out.
>> Mr. Secret,
>> Mr. Mayor, I believe there's some
ambiguity between the uh statutes.
Um the referendum that we're talking
about is only, as I understand it, is
only in the annexation
statute.
um because of the ambiguity as my
colleagues have pointed out for this
occasion but future occasions we really
need to know the right way for the
public to u appeal uh decision. So uh
clarification is what we're after. Uh
we're not stopping the the count or the
certification. So I'm I will support
this tonight. Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mr. Mayor through you
be a no vote. Reason is plain language
states any ordinance can have
petition and go to a referendum. It's
clear in Wyoming law. Really, it's clear
in constitutional law even for our whole
country. So that's why I will not
support. Let's just see what happens if
there's enough signatures and if there
will be referendum. Thank you
>> Dr. Em.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor. Through you. We
have a responsibility as elected
officials to ensure that we are
providing effective governance and um
making sure that we are meeting the rule
of law and um
the processes that are necessary to to
have a successful, efficient and
effective government,
which is why I'm going to vote for this
as well. We're responsible to make sure
that we're listening to the people that
we serve, which we have done numerous
times in this process. But this is one
more example of us honoring people's
right to um go forward and make their
feelings be known. So to me, this is the
best of all worlds. It helps us clarify
that we're conducting government
appropriately while making sure that the
voices of people in the community are
being served, being heard. Sorry.
And Mr. Mr. Mayor, through you also that
our constituents get to realize
uh that what they signed is
not going to prevent the owner of that
property continuing to move forward with
their plans. Uh it'll just be moving
forward in the county with less
regulation than what the city has. So,
uh, if you signed that, um, referendum
thinking that you were stopping a data
center from going in in that annexation,
uh, that is not the case.
So, if I could with your indulgence,
maybe just for the people watching or
want to read about this, maybe just kind
of lay out what's going on. Um, recently
we passed an ordinance to annex a little
over 3,000 acres. Um it was a owner
initiated annexation and it passed this
governing body. Um
there is in title 22 of state law uh a
referendum option where if people don't
like what the governing body does, they
can raise uh enough signatures to either
force us to make one of two choices.
That's 10% of the registered voters in
in the city of Cheyenne. we could either
repeal our ordinance or we can put it
into a referendum for the voters to
decide whether the governing body's
action was one that should stand or not.
um that was in fine I believe in title
22 but in title 15149
um it says that an annexation is the
appeal for that is in district court and
u and so that that's the question the
the law and annexation says you have to
appeal in district court but there is
this other thing that says you can do a
referendum and we we're not clear on
what is the correct way to um I guess um
appeal an annexation and so what the
motion that was made by this governing
body is is to ask the courts to
determine what the correct path forward
is for an annexation appeal. And uh so
that's what we're going to direct the at
least I think that's what we're going to
direct this evening uh would be to ask
our city attorney to uh ask the court
for that clarification and then we'll
know for now not only for this one but
also uh for any future annexation the
correct way for the public to be able to
appeal that. And so is there anybody
else in the governing body wants to
speak to it? If not, the motion is to
direct um our city attorney to uh to
file those uh declaratory judgment to
get that um clarification. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed?
>> No.
>> Mr. Moody is a no. The uh resolution, I
guess they call it a resolution has been
adopted. And uh I believe if there's
another further business for this
governing body, we're adjourned.